# Mayur Vishwasrao

# **Professional Summary**

Experienced data scientist having 5+ years of experience in Machine learning, Deep learning, and NLP with demonstrated history of working in the industries like, Oil & energy, Healthcare, Banking & Finance, Legal, Retail, Telecom, etc.

## Employment history

## Lead Engineer, HCL Technologies. Pune

May. 2017 - Present

- Built a generative based conversational Chatbot using deep learning models such as Seq2seq, RNN, and LSTM for telecom client
- Worked on Short Text Summarization using Naïve Bayes model for healthcare client
- Developed a HR analytics tools for HCL internal recruitment team using Rshiny
- Built a binary classification model using Bi-LSTM model for healthcare client
- Text classification using machine-learning algorithms such as Random forest, SVM, Naïve Bayes etc.
- Built a named entity model for healthcare client
- Extensive Knowledge of NLP techniques such as POS tagging, Lemmatization, NER, stemming, Tokenization, word2vec (Skip-gram, Continuous bag of word), and glove embeddings
- Extensive knowledge of using Machine Learning techniques such as Decision tree, SVM, Random forest, Ordinary Least Squares, Logistic regression, k-Nearest Neighbour, CHAID, Clustering etc. in R, Python
- Extensive knowledge of Deep learning models such as seq2seq, LSTM, LSTM with attention, Bi-Directional LSTM, GRU, with tensor flow framework

## Machine Learning Engineer, Futurism Technologies Pvt Ltd. Pune

Dec. 2016 - Apr. 2017

- Developed a conversational Chatbot using deep learning models- Seq2seq, LSTM, and GRII
- Built an automated email auto responder system using LSTM with Attention layer model
- Churn prediction using Logistic Regression

## Data Scientist, BancTec TPS India Pvt. Ltd. Pune

May. 2015 – Oct. 2016

- Identify business problems, translate it into analytical framework and propose a structured solution in line with business objective
- Built a highly accurate, user friendly, energy-forecasting platform for a powersupply client company to use across all of their market areas
- Developed an Energy consumption forecasting model using Multiple linear regression in R
- Built algorithms using Natural Language Processing (NLP) for Data Extraction
- Built models for data and fields extraction using machine learning for legal, healthcare, and banking domain
- Text processing and Information Extraction using R programming and Python Technology

## Personal info

#### Phone:

+91-8208253383

#### Email:

mayurvishwasrao6@gmail.com

#### Address:

Pune

## Skills

Python



**R-Software** 



Supervised Machine Learning: Linear/Logistic/Polynomial/Lasso/Ridge Regression Techniques, Decision Tree, Support Vector Machine, Random Forest, Naive Bayes, KNN



Unsupervised Machine Learning: Kmeans Clustering, Hierarchical Clustering



Deep Learning: RNN, LSTM, Seq2Seq, Bi-LSTM



NLP: POS Tagging, Lemmatization, Tokenization, Chunking, NER, etc.



Advanced Forecasting Methodologies: AR, MA, ARMA, ARIMA



**Dimension Reduction Techniques:** 



- Worked on Predictive analytics projects in python using pandas, Scikit-learn, Nltk, Numpy, and Scipy libraries
- Communicate findings clearly to both technical & non-technical audiences to approach a business challenge

## Research Analyst, CRISIL Pvt Ltd. Pune

Dec. 2013 - May. 2015

- Forecasted quarterly sales of manufacturing firms using time series models using SAS tool
- Worked on model validation projects for different banks in the US
- Sound Knowledge of extracting data using different API's (Application Programming Interface) for data analysis for e.g. Twitter API, from where data is extracted for predictive analytics models
- Worked on Python with projects such as Sentiments Analysis of Social Media Websites like Twitter, Facebook, and movie review analysis using Twitter, Facebook, and Rotten Tomatoes databases
- Maintained database for voluntary insurance market of the US and providing direct comparison of client's product offering vis-à-vis competitors
- Performed competitive and premium pricing analysis of insurance companies in the US for voluntary worksite group products. Also indexed and maintained database of insurance companies' disclosures
- Worked on special projects such as Sentimental Analysis of India Budget 2014-15
- Company profiles: Worked out detailed profiles, comprising overview, financials, geography, products and management, and prepared newsletters to track industries on a regular basis, capturing developments such as product launch, management changes, expansion or divestment etc.

## Education

## Gokhale Institute of Politics & Economics, Pune

M.Sc. (Financial Economics), Aug. 2013

## **Pune University, Pune**

B.Sc. (Statistics), Jul. 2011

## Certifications

- NSE (National Stock Exchange) Certified Capital Market Professional Module
- Certified Financial Modelling in MS-Excel

**Data Visualization** 









Other Skills: SAS, Weka, E-views, MS Excel, SQL



